Hello everyone and welcome to
English POD, my name is Marco.
My name is Catherine
and today we're going to be
helping you find someone
to help out around the house.
That's right, so we're looking for someone
to help us do some things around the house,
so we're going to talk
about this more in-depth,
but first let's take a look at
one word on vocabulary preview.
Very cablery preview.
So the beginning of today's dialogue
has to do with a newspaper ad.
We are writing an ad for the newspaper.
Now what exactly is a newspaper ad Marco?
That's right, so in the newspapers, usually
there is a section called the classifieds
where people post
ads or advertisements or
adverts where maybe they're selling their
car or they're looking to hire people.
So this is what a newspaper
ad is, you're selling something,
you're buying something or
maybe you want to hire people, etc.
It is a basically an advertisement
in the newspaper to find help.
Alright, so let's listen to our
dialogue and when we come back
we'll be talking more about the
words and phrases you've heard.
Can you help me write a newspaper ad?
Sure, now what are you
looking to buy yourself?
Actually, I want to hire someone
to help me around the house.
Oh, you want to get them made?
Well, I think it's better if you call
her a cleaning lady or domestic help.
Okay, so what do you want her to do?
Well let's see, I wanted to come in three
times a week for a couple of hours to clean
the kitchen, bathroom and
maybe do some cooking.
Got it, and how much
do you offer per month?
I would pay her hourly, I don't
know what the going rate is though.
I know for sure it's more
than minimum wage,
but maybe you should just negotiate
with the person that answers the ad.
Great, thanks for your help.
Alright, we're back, so now let's
take a look at language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
Okay, so first of
all, today Marco, the
advertisement is about
wanting to hire someone.
This is an important verb, especially
when we're trying to find help.
The verb to hire.
That's right, so to hire means to give
someone work to offer a contract to someone.
Okay, so my boss hired me three years ago,
I mean he gave me a job three years ago.
That's right.
But this is not just for office
jobs, this is for all kinds of jobs.
So what about cutting your
grass or doing your lawn?
That's right, so you
can hire a gardener, for
example, and it's
basically the same thing.
It means that you're going to
pay someone to work for you.
Okay, so today we wanted to
hire a maid, M-A-I-D, a maid.
But this is a little bit
old-fashioned, this word.
What does a maid do or what did a maid do?
Well, a maid is basically a
woman, a female servant,
so to say, a person
that basically serves you.
Alright, so she cleans
the house, she maybe
puts the covers on the beds,
washes the dishes, cooks.
That does all of these domestic
things, so she works around the house.
But because there's a bad association, we
don't like to think, oh, we have servants.
We don't say maid anymore, we
have two other ways of saying this word.
That's right, so we could
say that we want to hire
a cleaning lady, or we
want to hire domestic help.
Okay, now there's an important
difference between these two words.
First of all, cleaning
lady is a woman, a lady.
And she is someone who only cleans.
She doesn't take care of your children, she
doesn't walk your dog, she basically just
cleans the house, washes
the dishes, cleans the
clothes, washes the floors,
so she's a cleaning lady.
Now, domestic help, this
is a little bit more general.
Right, so domestic
help would be a little
bit more in-depth of
what the person is going
to do, so will help with the domestic
work, with domestic meaning the house.
So this person will
maybe cook for you, clean
the house, take care of the kids, do
everything that is associated with the house.
So it's important to
see that domestic means
something that has
to do with the house.
This is help man or woman in the house.
Right.
Alright, so that's all
we have for language
takeaway, but we do have
another section, fluency
builder, which we're going to look
at some great words and phrases.
Alright, so first on fluency builder, let's
take a look at how we're going to pay the
person, because
obviously we were saying
that we want to hire
this person, we're going
to pay them, so how are
we going to pay them?
The person said, "I would pay the
woman her hourly, I would pay her hourly."
Okay, so this is the rate, this
is how much she will be paid.
And we don't say she
will be paid $10,000 per
year, we say she will
be paid $10 per hour.
Right.
So we pay per hour,
this is paying her hourly.
Right, so if you have
an hourly wage, that
means that you get
paid per hour in contrast
with a salary, that means that you
would get a fixed amount every month.
Alright, so if the
monthly salary is $1,000,
for example, you could
break that down and
say, but every day you
earn 100, you work 10 days.
But if it's hourly, you
say you'll get paid $10 per
hour, so if you work 4 hours
today, you will earn $40.
That's right.
Okay, so now we want
to pay the clean lady
hourly, but we don't
know what the going rate is.
Going rate, going.
So this is an interesting
phrase, and it's
important to notice
that it's not going rate
is an amount of money,
but it's not always the same.
Right.
It depends on the industry.
So the going rate for
a teacher is different
from the going rate
for a cleaning lady,
which is different from the going rate for
a language tutor, like an English tutor.
So first of all, the
going rate is how much
these people, these cleaning
ladies, normally earn is an average.
Right.
So you would, yeah, you
would usually calculate
it, say the approximate going rate is
between maybe $8 to $10 per hour.
So it's not like an exact
amount, you would
say the going rate is more
or less a certain amount.
It's not exact.
So you might ask your friends,
what do you pay your cleaning lady?
And one friend says,
oh, I pay $12 per hour.
And my other friend says,
oh, I pay about $8 per hour.
So to me, it sounds like the
going rate is about $10 per hour.
Right.
So we're not really sure
what the going rate is.
So our friend says, well, you know what,
I'm sure it's more than minimum wage.
Now minimum wage is
actually something that
the government decides on or either the
federal government and America or the state.
And each state will have
a number that they say
that is the least you can
pay a person per hour.
Right.
So it is the law.
If you pay less, it's illegal.
It's illegal.
And this is because we expect
everyone to be treated fairly.
Right.
So you don't want to
take advantage of people.
No.
And so, for example,
in America in my state,
Illinois, I think the minimum
wage is $7.25 per hour.
Oh, really?
Wow.
It's pretty high.
And this is because
people need to pay for
health care and cars
and houses and children.
So we say the least you
can pay someone is $7.25.
Now this is different.
As you said, it could be
different from state to state, right?
Because I know in some states, if I'm
not mistaken, it's like $5.50 or something.
Yeah, some states is $5.
It depends on the cost of living.
If it's cheap to rent
an apartment or to find
transportation, then obviously the
minimum wage is going to be lower.
Obviously, there's no maximum wage.
There's no number
that is the most you can
pay some, but all states
have a minimum wage.
It's the least that you
can pay someone per hour.
Okay.
And now for our last
phrase, we don't know
what the minimum wage is, we're
not really sure what the going rate is.
So we should just negotiate with
the person that answers the ad.
All right.
Now to negotiate is a great verb.
It's something that
all of us do all the time.
So to negotiate means to try and
compromise or to reach an agreement.
And so maybe I say the
most I will pay is your $11.
So I say, okay, I'll pay you $9.
And I say, no, I'll take 12.
Yeah, sorry.
12 is too much.
I'll pay you 10.
Okay.
11.
Agreed.
Okay.
So it's a way of reaching an agreement like
you say, where both sides have their goals.
Right.
And a price that is the
best for both parties.
That's right.
So it's basically a verb to negotiate.
And this is what you
do in, like you said,
in many circumstances, especially
when you're getting a job.
Yes.
All right.
So let's listen to the dialogue one
last time and we'll be back in a bit.
Can you help me write a newspaper ad?
Sure.
What are you looking to buy yourself?
Actually, I want to hire someone
to help me around the house.
Oh, you want to get a maid?
Well, I think it's better if you call
her a cleaning lady or domestic help.
Okay.
So what do you want her to do?
Well, let's see.
I wanted to come in
three times a week for a
couple of hours to clean the kitchen,
bathroom, and maybe do some cooking.
Got it.
And how much do you offer per month?
I would pay her hourly.
I don't know what the
going rate is, though.
I know for sure it's more
than minimum wage.
But maybe you should just negotiate
with the person that answers the ad.
Right.
Thanks for your help.
All right.
So talking about
minimum wage, is there any
exception to why a person would
earn less than minimum wage?
I don't believe so well, if they're
not legally employed, right?
So if you're talking
about people who we say
are under the table,
working under the table,
that means that they're
not working legally,
they're not paying taxes, then
maybe those people will be paid less.
What about waiters and waitresses?
I've heard that they earn less than
minimum wage, but because they earn tips.
This is true.
So most restaurants say, okay, we
will pay you as a waiter $3 an hour.
But because you will earn tips, you
will earn more than the minimum wage.
Right.
So this is a good exception.
Unfortunately, there's no promise.
If you have no customers,
you earn no tips, so
you're still earning less
than minimum wage.
But it's possible that
you also have many,
many customers, and
you earn lots of tips and
you make $15 an hour or something
much higher than the minimum wage.
That's right.
And actually being a
waiter or a waitress is
a very common job
that a lot of people have
when they're still in
school or over the summer.
And I've heard that it could be quite good
because Americans are pretty good tippers.
That's right.
Americans generally tip
between 15 and 20 percent.
No.
And you know that you have to tip because
your waiter does not earn a minimum wage.
Right.
And so there is this expectation.
So if your bill comes out
to like a hundred bucks, then
you are most definitely
going to leave at least a $20 tip.
Usually, yeah, $15 to $20,
$20 if it's that much money.
Wow.
That's very, very interesting, especially
considering that in many countries, tipping
is not really considered,
it's not expected
or it's not really
something that people do.
Exactly.
And in America, it is
something that you have to do.
So I think a lot of times when people come
to America, they don't expect to pay this.
There's tax.
There's tip.
So when you see a menu, remember
that the cost is a lot higher than you see.
Exactly.
All right.
Very, very interesting topic.
Let us know if you have any
questions, any doubts or comments.
You can find us at EnglishPod.com.
We'll see you guys there.
Bye.